A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Asia Programs, Regional Director, Office Files of Peter F. Geithner FA1532
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Asia Programs, Regional Director, Office Files of Peter F. Geithner
1970-1996
Rockefeller Archive Center
Geithner, Peter F.
Ford Foundation
FA1532
8.74 Cubic Feet 23 letter size document boxes
Scope and Contents
The collection contains the office files Peter F. Geithner created and managed during his career at the Ford Foundation. The collection is arranged into record groups. Each record group corresponds to a different position Geithner held at the Foundation. Throughout his time at the Foundation, Geithner's work primarily concentrated on program activity in Asia, and his last position at the Foundation before his retirement was Regional Director of Asia Programs.
To date, the collection contains two record groups:
Record Group 1 documents Geithner's position as Program Officer in Charge of the Developing Countries Program from 1981 to 1987.
Record Group 2 documents Geithner's position as Regional Director of Asia Programs from 1990 to 1996.
Records in the collection document the Ford Foundation's similar programming for China and Vietnam during periods of economic change and improved diplomatic relations with the United States. These time periods were the 1980s for China and the 1990s for Vietnam. Ford worked with agencies and government groups in the countries as well as with other foundations and research centers to support economic development and training, legal education, and improved international relations for China and Vietnam. This work which Geithner helped lead preceded the Foundation opening its field offices in Beijing, China in 1988 and Hanoi, Vietnam in 1996.
Files in the collection also show the Foundation's support for integrating sustainable resource management with economic and agricultural development in various Asian countries like Vietnam and Bangladesh through activities like social forestry.
Arrangement
Collection is comprised of two records groups and six series.
Original order was maintained as much as possible.
The collection arrangement is as follows:
Record Group 1. Developing Countries Program Office Files, 1970-1988
RG1 Series 1. Meeting and trip files, 1970-1987
RG1 Series 2. Subject files, 1973-1988
RG1 Series 2. Subject files. Subseries 1. China, 1979-1988
RG1 Series 2. Subject files. Subseries 2. General, 1973-1985
RG1 Series 3. Chronology files, 1981-1986
Record Group 2. Asia Programs Office Files, 1975-1996
RG2 Series 1. Conferences, 1991-1992
RG2 Series 2. Correspondence, 1989-1995
RG2 Series 3. Subject files, 1975-1996
RG2 Series 3. Subject files. Subseries 1. Vietnam, 1988-1995
RG2 Series 3. Subject files Subseries 2. General, 1975-1995
RG2 Series 3. Subject files Subseries 3. Bangladesh, 1991-1996
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files, and officers' papers were transferred to and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
This material was transferred to the RAC in various accessions between 2011 and 2023 and was ingested by the RAC as Accessions 2011:072, 2012:025, 2019:050, 2019:136, 2021:110, and 2023:017.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Biographical / Historical
The Asia Programs office originated in 1958 as a division of the Overseas Development program then called the Overseas Development/South and Southeast Asia. In 1966, South and Southeast Asia office shifted to the International Division program area as part of a Foundation reorganization and, in 1968, the office was renamed Asia and the Pacific. In 1981, the office became part of the Developing Countries Program. The Asia Programs became a full program area in 1989.
At various points throughout its history, the Asia Programs maintained field offices in: New Delhi, India; Jakarta, Indonesia; Dhaka, Bangladesh; Bangkok, Thailand; Manila, Philippines; and Hanoi, Vietnam.
Ford Foundation; Agricultural development projects; Africa; Asia; Bangladesh; China; Economic development; Economics -- Study and teaching; Educational exchanges; Forestry projects -- Asia; Latin America; Law -- Study and teaching; Middle East; Reproductive health; Social forestry programs; SouthEast Asia; Vietnam; United States
- Record Group 1 Developing Countries Program Office Files, 1970-1988; 1; 5.7 Cubic Feet 15 letter size document boxes
  Arrangement
  Record Group 1 is comprised of three series.
  RG1 Series 1. Meeting and trip files, 1970-1987
  RG1 Series 2. Subject files, 1973-1988
  RG1 Series 2. Subject files. Subseries 1. China, 1979-1988
  RG1 Series 2. Subject files. Subseries 2. General, 1973-1985
  RG1 Series 3. Chronology files, 1981-1986
  Scope and Contents
  This record group contains the office files Peter F. Geithner created during his time as Program Officer in Charge of the Ford Foundation's Developing Countries Program (DCP). Materials span from Geithner's entire 1981 to 1987 tenure as DCP Program Officer in Charge. The collection is comprised of meeting and trip files, subject files, and chronology files.
  Meeting files document the work that Geithner, other Ford Foundation staff members such as the different Field Officer Representatives, and external individuals and organizations completed for organizing, participating in, and reporting on various Ford Foundation program meetings and other types of events and conferences. Trip files document Geithner's visits to various countries and Ford Foundation field offices as well as the visits he helped organize for individuals like Foundation Board of Trustees Members.
  Subject files largely concern the Foundation's programming regarding China. There are also some more general DCP administrative and program subject files. The chronology files contain copies of correspondence Geithner sent throughout his time as DCP Program Officer in Charge.
  Geithner's files provide insight into the Developing Countries Program's interest in and support of initiatives concerning economic development, agricultural development, child survival, and reproductive health in countries throughout Africa, Asia, Latin America, and the Middle East during the 1980s. They also document the Foundation's growing program activity related to China ahead of its opening its Beijing, China field office in 1988.
  - Meeting and trip files, 1970-1987; 1; 1.52 Cubic Feet 4 letter size document boxes
    The series contains the meeting and trip files that Peter F. Geithner created during his time as Program Officer in Charge of the Ford Foundation's Developing Countries Program (DCP). Meeting files generally concern the review of the Foundation's actions regarding issues such as employment and income generation, child survival, and reproductive health in developing countries throughout Africa, Asia, Latin America, and the Middle East as well as the planning and organization of additional actions to support the study and tackling of these issues. The series also includes meeting files that document other types of events such as a meeting the Ford Foundation organized between different foundations and Indira Gandhi, the Prime Minister of India, to discuss economic development and grant clearance procedures in India. Trip files concern the different visits Geithner organized for himself and other individuals like members of the Ford Foundation Board of Trustees to various countries and Foundation field offices. Some of the travel advisory memos within the trip files provide insight into the political situations and trends of these countries such as the opposition to President Ferdinand Marcos in the Philippines and the violence of Shining Path (Sendero Luminoso) in Peru.
    Although most of the series' files were created during Geithner's tenure as Program Officer in Charge of the DCP, there does appear to be some material that was created just before Geithner moved from his previous position as Representative for Southeast Asia in the Bangkok, Thailand Regional Office.
    - Education and Culture Meeting, Bali, Indonesia, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Employment and Income Generation (EIG) Meeting, Dhaka, Bangladesh, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
    - Fiscal Year 1986 Developing Countries Program (DCP) Program Reviews, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Rural Poverty and Resources Program (RPR) Common Property Resources (CPR) Meeting, Indonesia, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Rural Poverty and Resources Program (RPR) Meeting, Cairo, Egypt, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Child Survival/Population Meeting, Kathmandu, Nepal, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - India Festival - Metropolitan Museum of Art Reception, 1985; File includes 3 still images. (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
      File includes 3 photographs of the Ford Foundation New Delhi, India Regional Office staff in 1985 captioned "With Fond Remembrance, Ford Foundation New Delhi Staff, September 1985".
    - Child Survival/Fair Start Meeting, Bangkok, Thailand, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - India Annual Program Visit, 1982-1985 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Bangladesh trips, 1972-1987 (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
    - Prime Minister of India Indira Gandhi Meeting with Private Philanthropies and Related Organizations, 1970-1982 (Box 3, Folder 15-17)
    - Human Rights and International Affairs Programs Meetings, Geneva, Switzerland, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Lima, Peru and Bogota and Cali, Colombia trip, 1980-1984 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Rodrigo Botero, Ford Foundation Trustee - East and Southeast Asia trip, 1984-1985; File contains a set of still images. (Box 3, Folder 20)
      File contains a group of photographs taken during Ford Foundation Board of Trustees' Member Rodrigo Botero's visit to countries in East and Southeast Asia in 1985. Individuals captured in the photographs include Botero, his wife Louise, and Han Sung-joo, Director of the Asiatic Research Center and professor of international relations at Korea University and the Boteros' host in Korea. Photographs were originally contained in a small album from Bangkok, Thailand.
    - North Africa and Middle East trips, 1981-1983 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Southeast Asia trip, 1984-1985 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Thailand trip, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - New York City, New York trip, 1980-1981 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - East Africa trip, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Tom Wyman, Ford Foundation Trustee - India trip, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Subject files, 1973-1988; 2; 1.9 Cubic Feet 5 letter size document boxes
    This series contains the subject files Peter F. Geithner created when he served as Program Officer in Charge of the Ford Foundation's Developing Countries Program between 1981 and 1987. It is comprised of two subseries. The first subseries contains records specifically concerning the Foundation's programming for China, and the second subseries contains records documenting more general DCP administration and program activities.
    The bulk of the series is contained within the China subseries. During the 1980s, the Ford Foundation expanded its programming for China when diplomatic relations between China and the United States improved. The Foundation would later open its Beijing, China field office in 1988, and Geithner would serve as the Foundation's first China Representative. One file of Geithner's correspondence from that position is included at the end of the first subseries.
    In addition to correspondence, the series contains memos, reports, notes, drafts, news clippings, and meeting materials.
    - China, 1979-1988; 1; 1.62 Cubic Feet 4.25 letter size document boxes
      The China subject files subseries documents the work led by Developing Countries Program Officer in Charge Peter F. Geithner regarding the Ford Foundation's programming for China in the 1980s. Materials show the Ford Foundation's communication and collaboration with organizations like the Chinese Academy of Social Sciences (CASS) during a time when China underwent economic and political changes and shifting international relations. Foundation programming largely centered on education and research with specific focuses on economics education and training in China, educational exchanges between China and the U.S., law education, Chinese international relations, and research on the changes occurring in China.
      The work of groups like the United States Committee on Economics Education and Research in China (CEERC) and the U.S. Committee on Legal Education Exchange with China (CLEEC) are documented in the subseries.
      - United States Committee on Economics Education and Research in China (CEERC), 1982-1986 (Box 5, Folder 27-29)
      - Ford Foundation in China, part 1, 1979-1987 (Box 5, Folder 30-31)
      - Ford Foundation in China, part 2, 1980-1986 (Box 6, Folder 32-33)
      - China - Economics education, 1986-1987 (Box 6, Folder 34)
      - China – Human rights, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 35)
      - Ford Foundation Trustees' Human Rights, Governance, and International Affairs paper - China and the Ford Foundation, 1982-1986 (Box 6, Folder 36)
      - China – Economics and management training, 1979-1983 (Box 6, Folder 37)
      - China Prime Minister Zhao Ziyang 1984 United States visit, 1981-1984 (Box 7, Folder 38)
      - China - Reform and student protests, 1986-1987 (Box 7, Folder 39)
      - American Council of Learned Societies (ACLS)/Social Science Research Council (SSRC) Joint Committee on Chinese Studies (JCCS) workshop - Price and wage reform in China, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 40-41)
      - China – International Research and Exchanges Board (IREX) delegation of Chinese specialists on the Soviet Union and Eastern Europe, 1984-1986 (Box 7, Folder 42)
      - China – United States Committee on Legal Education Exchange with China (CLEEC), 1982-1987 (Box 8, Folder 43-45)
      - China - United States Committee on Legal Education Exchange with China (CLEEC), 1985 (Box 8, Folder 46)
      - China - International relations, 1981-1986 (Box 8, Folder 47-48)
      - Peter Geithner China Representative miscellaneous 1988 correspondence (Box 9, Folder 49-50)
    - General, 1973-1985; 2; .28 Cubic Feet .75 letter size document box
      The general subject files subseries documents miscellaneous administrative and program activities of the Ford Foundation's Developing Countries Program in the 1980s when Peter F. Geithner was Program Officer in Charge. One of the primary areas of administrative concern centered around DCP policy and organization changes during a time of Ford Foundation Program Division reorganization.
      - International Personnel Association (IPA), 1983 (Box 9, Folder 51)
      - Operations/Ford Foundation reorganization - Developing Countries Program, 1981-1982 (Box 9, Folder 52)
      - Operations/Ford Foundation reorganization - Developing Countries Program, 1981 (Box 9, Folder 53)
      - Operations/Ford Foundation reorganization - Developing Countries Program recruitment, 1981-1982 (Box 9, Folder 54)
      - Operations/Ford Foundation reorganization - Asia and Pacific Program Staff profile, 1973-1976 (Box 9, Folder 55)
      - Private giving - International grantmaking, 1981-1985 (Box 9, Folder 56)
      - South Africa - Richard Horovitz memo and news articles, 1981-1982 (Box 9, Folder 57)
      - Woodrow Wilson Center, 1981-1985 (Box 9, Folder 58)
  - Chronology files, 1981-1986; 3; 2.28 Cubic Feet 6 letter size document boxes
    This series contains the chronology files Peter F. Geithner created and maintained during his tenure as Program Officer in Charge of the Ford Foundation's Developing Countries Program between 1981 and 1987. Files in the series span from 1981 to 1986.
    Each chronology file in the series contains copies of the messages Geithner's office sent during a specific block of time. Within those blocks of time, the correspondence is arranged alphabetically, usually by the person to whom the correspondence is addressed but sometimes by the subject of the correspondence.
    The chronology files contain Geithner's internal Ford Foundation communications as well as his messages to external individuals. Within the Foundation, Geithner frequently wrote to:
    William Carmichael – Developing Countries Program Vice President
    Franklin Thomas – Ford Foundation President
    Enid C.B. Schoettle – International Affairs Program (IAP) Program Officer in Charge
    Field Office Representatives as a group and several individually such as Lincoln Chen (New Delhi, India), Adrienne Germain (Dhaka, Bangladesh (Dacca)), Thomas Kessinger (Jakarta, Indonesia), Goran Hyden (Nairobi, Kenya), and John Gerhart (Cairo, Egypt)
    Joan Carroll – Office of Personnel Services
    External individuals include representatives from various foundations, research centers, universities, and governments. Numerous messages to representative of the Chinese Academy of Social Sciences (CASS) show the Ford Foundation's increasing program interest regarding China.
    The correspondence documents various DCP administrative and program activities like trips and visits, program reviews, program budgets, policies, hiring, requests for Ford Foundation support, and grants.
    - October 1981 - April 1982 Chron File (alphabetical), 1981-1982 (Box 10, Folder 59-61)
    - May 1982 - September 1982 Chron File (alphabetical) (Box 10, Folder 62-64)
    - October 1982 - April 1983 Chron File (alphabetical), 1982-1983 (Box 11, Folder 65-67)
    - May 1983 - September 1983 Chron File (alphabetical) (Box 11, Folder 68-70)
    - October 1983 - January 1984 Chron File (alphabetical), 1983-1984 (Box 12, Folder 71-73)
    - February 1984 - July 1984 Chron File (alphabetical) (Box 12, Folder 74-76)
    - August 1984 - January 1985 Chron File, (alphabetical), 1984-1985 (Box 13, Folder 77-79)
    - February 1985 - July 1985 Chron File, A-R (alphabetical) (Box 13, Folder 80-81)
    - February 1985 - July 1985 Chron File, S-Z (alphabetical) (Box 14, Folder 82)
    - August 1985 - January 1986 Chron File (alphabetical), 1985-1986 (Box 14, Folder 83-85)
    - February 1986 - July 1986 Chron File, A-H (alphabetical) (Box 14, Folder 86)
    - February 1986 - July 1986 Chron Fie, I-Z (alphabetical) (Box 15, Folder 87-88)
- Record Group 2 Asia Programs Office Files, 1975-1996; 2; 3.04 Cubic Feet 8 letter size document boxes
  Record Group 2 is comprised of three series.
  RG2 Series 1. Conferences, 1991-1992
  RG2 Series 2. Correspondence, 1989-1995
  RG2 Series 3. Subject files, 1975-1996
  RG2 Series 3. Subject files. Subseries 1. Vietnam, 1988-1995
  RG2 Series 3. Subject files. Subseries 2. General, 1975-1995
  RG2 Series 3. Subject files. Subseries 3. Bangladesh, 1991-1996
  The second record group in the collection contains the office files Peter F. Geithner created when he served as Regional Director of the Ford Foundation's Asia programs. Materials span across Geithner's entire 1990 to 1996 career as Asia Programs' Regional Director. The record group is comprised of conference files, correspondence, and subject files.
  A significant portion of the record group's contents concern the Ford Foundation's programming for Vietnam and Southeast Asia during the 1990s. All of the conference and correspondence files pertain to Vietnam as does a section of the subject files. Within the Asia Programs, programming for Vietnam was largely carried out by the Southeast Asia Program based in the Foundation's Jakarta, Indonesia Office under Representatives David Winder and Mary Zurbuchen and the Bangkok, Thailand Office under Program Officer for Vietnam, Mark Sidel.
  Other subject files in the record group show the Asia Programs' broader administrative and program activities. There is also a specific set of subject files concerning programming for Bangladesh and the Ford Foundation's Dhaka Field Office.
  - Conferences, 1991-1992; 1; .095 Cubic Feet .25 letter size document box
    This series contains conference files Peter F. Geithner created when he served as the Ford Foundation's Regional Director of Asia Programs. The conferences documented in the series concerned Vietnam and Southeast Asia, reflecting the Foundation's program interest in the region during the 1990s.
    The files contain typical material formats for preparing for and participating in meetings such as correspondence, notes, agendas, background readings, reports, and a speech. Materials in the series originate from the beginning of Geithner's role as Asia Programs Regional Director in the early 1990s.
    - Aspen Institute Indochina Policy Program, 1991-1992 (Box 16, Folder 89)
    - Vietnam - Conference on the Challenges of Vietnam's Reconstruction: Domestic and International Issues, Arlington, Virginia, 1992 (Box 16, Folder 90)
  - Correspondence, 1989-1995; 2; .66 Cubic Feet 1.75 letter size document boxes
    This series contains the correspondence files Peter Geithner created and maintained when he served as Regional Director of Asia Programs at the Ford Foundation. The files are arranged by the subject of the correspondence, and they include correspondence both sent and received by Geithner as well as the correspondence of other Ford Foundation staff which related to Geithner's work as Asia Programs Regional Director. The files in the series all concern the Foundation's work related to Vietnam and Southeast Asia in the first half of the 1990s.
    The correspondence in the series is with other Ford Foundation staff, external foundations, Vietnamese agencies, and research centers. It shows the Foundation's interests in supporting economic development and training, rural and agricultural development, legal education, educational exchanges, and improvement of Vietnam-United States relations. The Foundation worked closely with the Vietnamese government for permission of its activities in the country and for its grant recipients traveling in and out of Vietnam.
    The files show how much of the Foundation's Vietnam programming largely came out of its Bangkok, Thailand office. Foundation Representatives for Southeast Asia (based out of the Jakarta, Indonesia office) David Winder and Mary Zurbuchen (who succeeded Winder) and Program Officer for Vietnam Mark Sidel contributed significantly to the correspondence in the series. In addition to correspondence, the files also contain notes, drafts, reports, and news clippings.
    - Vietnam - National Center for Social Sciences of Vietnam (NCSS), 1990-1993 (Box 16, Folder 91)
    - Vietnam - University of California, Berkeley, 1991-1993 (Box 16, Folder 92)
    - Vietnam - Harvard Institute for International Development (HIID), 1991-1992 (Box 16, Folder 93)
      Report "Socialist Republic of Vietnam university consolidation project: economic issues for higher education in Vietnam draft, 1992" was removed from file prior to transfer to the Rockefeller Archive Center and put into the Ford Foundation Catalogued Reports collection as Catalogued Report 019564. Report can be accessed on the RAC Virtual Vault.
    - Vietnam - Law and legal reform, 1991-1992 (Box 16, Folder 94)
    - Vietnam Central Institute for Economic Management (CIEM), 1991-1993 (Box 16, Folder 95)
    - Vietnam - Volunteers in Asia (VIA), 1991-1992 (Box 16, Folder 96)
    - Vietnam Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 1991-1993 (Box 16, Folder 97)
    - Vietnam -- People's Aid Coordination Committee (PACCOM), 1991 August (Box 16, Folder 98)
    - General communications regarding Vietnam - Travel, government, Project LINK, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 99)
    - Vietnam - Upland management, 1989-1992 (Box 17, Folder 100)
    - The Economics Institute, 1991-1992 (Box 17, Folder 101)
    - Vietnam - National Economics University (NEU), 1991-1993 (Box 17, Folder 102)